Career Action Center-Resource Center for Women Records, 1972-2002: A Guide M1654
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
Career Action Center-Resource Center for Women Records
1972-2002
M1654
Department of Special Collections and University Archives
17.0 Linear feet (29 manuscript boxes, 2 flat boxes)
The collection contains materials related to the founding and history of the Career Action Center-Resource Center for Women, a job resource center active on the San Francisco Peninsula between 1973-2002.
Career Action Center.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Arrangement
The collection is arranged into five series:
Series I. History
Series II. Administrative Records
Series III. Financial Records and Fund Development
Series IV. Programs and Publications
Series V. Audio/Visual Materials
Scope and Content of Collection
This collection includes administrative records, financial records, photographs, scrapbooks, publications, program materials, video and audio tapes related to the founding and history of the Career Action Center-Resource Center for Women, a job resource center active on the San Francisco Peninsula between 1973 – 2002.
Organizational History
The Resource Center for Women (1973-2002, name changed to Career Action Center in 1988) was founded in 1972 by five women, Eleanor Shelling, Mary Morley Perez, Peggy Kelly Larsen, Marylyn Morrell, and Martha Faust Hargadon, who met at a career planning workshop called “the Next Step” sponsored by the Stanford Faculty Women’s Club. The nonprofit center began with a staff of volunteers and the goal of providing guidance to a variety of women in transition, including well-educated women, women re-entering the work force, women with children, widowed and divorced women, and women active in their communities as volunteers. It was supported by individual and corporate donations, membership subscriptions, and grants. The center’s original mission statement read: “The Center will serve women who wish to make informed choices about the direction of their lives. It will be an active link between clients who want to use their talents more fully and the educational, volunteer, and salaried work opportunities on the San Francisco Peninsula.” Its first newspaper ad read “WOMEN interested in professional part-time or short term work send resumes to Resource Center for Women, 1176 Emerson, P.A;” and its first workshop, held at Foothill College January 1973, was entitled “Focus on Choice: Women in Transition.” Over two thousand women contacted the center in its first year for employment assistance, education programs, counseling, referrals, and use of the center library.
Bertha Bodek Kalson served as the center librarian from 1974 to 1989, starting with a shoe box of clippings and developing a collection that became a model for local organizations. The collection included college catalogs, statistical surveys, career guides, materials on women’s organizations, subject files and video tapes. By 2000 membership was down and the center was struggling to survive as a low-cost career services provider. After exploring merger possibilities the center closed in 2002. Its library was donated to the North Valley Job Training Consortium and a fund for career development was established through the Women’s Foundation.
Career Action Center Directors
Eleanor R. Shelling, 1974-1979
Judith Ousterhout, Executive Director, 1979-1984
Gail Stypula, Executive Director, 1984-1988
Diane Pelosi Saign, Executive Director, 1990-1998
Sharon Bray, Chief Executive Officer, 1998-2000
Emily Mora, Chief Executive Officer, 2000-2001
Acquisition Information
Accession number: 2008-339. The Career Action Center Records were given to Stanford University for the Department of Special Collections by Marylyn Morrell in March 2008.
Career Action Center.
- Series I. HISTORY
  Scope and Content
  This series includes original plans for the center, information about events and course offerings, materials from the 1977 time capsule, special events materials, posters and photographs, and scrapbooks.
  - History, 1972 (Box 1)
  - History, 1972-1973 (Box 1)
  - History, 1973 (Box 1)
  - History, 1974 (3 folders) (Box 1)
  - History, 1975 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - History, 1976 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - History 1977 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - History, 1978 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - History, 1979 (2 folders) (Box 2)
  - History, 1980-1989 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - History, 1990-1999 (2 folders) (Box 3)
  - History, 2000-2002 (Box 3)
  - Resource Center for Women proposal, circa 1972-1978 (3 folders) (Box 3)
  - Grants and fundraising, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Letters of endorsement, 1972-1973 (Box 4)
  - Five founders photo, 1973 (Flat-box 6)
  - Scrapbook, Bertha Kalson, 1973-1989 (Box 5)
  - Time capsule, 1977 (5 folders) (Box 4)
  - Time capsule, 1977 (Flat-box 6)
  - History steering committee, 1992 (Box 7)
  - Twentieth anniversary, 1993 (Box 7)
  - Twentieth anniversary photo collage, 1993 (Flat-box 6)
  - Goodbye Sherman St. party, 1996 (Box 7)
  - Twenty-fifth anniversary, 1998 (Box 7)
  - Funny file (Box 7)
  - Closure, 2002 (Box 7)
  - Posters and awards (Flat-box 6)
  - Shirt (Flat-box 6)
  - Scrapbook, clippings (Flat-box 6)
  - Scrapbook, Pinnacle, 1995-1996 (Flat-box 8)
  - Scrapbook, opening day, 1996 (Flat-box 8)
  - Scrapbook (Flat-box 8)
  - Guest register (Flat-box 8)
  - Lapel pins (Flat-box 8)
  - Miscellaneous history (5 folders) (Box 9)
  - Publicity photos (Box 10)
  - Photos, twentieth anniversary, 1993 (Box 10)
  - Photos, holiday party, 1994 (Box 10)
  - Photos, volunteer luncheon, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Photos, open house, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Photos, Women of Vision, 1996 (Box 10)
  - Photos, Kahn party, 1997 (Box 10)
  - Photos, Women of Vision, 1999 (Box 10)
  - Miscellaneous photos (11 folders) (Box 10)
- Series II. ADMINISTRATIVE RECORDS
  This series includes original funding proposal, articles of incorporation and by-laws, organizational planning materials and annual reports, board of directors meeting minutes and handbook, statistics, personnel, volunteers, and materials related to closure.
  - Articles of incorporation and by-laws (Box 11)
  - Funding proposal, 1973 (Box 11)
  - Annual reports, 1973-1979 (Box 11)
  - Annual reports, 1980-1989 (Box 11)
  - Annual reports, 1990-1999 (Box 11)
  - Planning, 1972-1973 (Box 11)
  - Planning, 1976-1977 (Box 11)
  - Planning, 1977-1978 (Box 11)
  - Planning, 1984-1989 (Box 11)
  - Planning, 1992-1993 (Box 12)
  - Planning, 2000 (Box 12)
  - Board of directors, 1978 (Box 12)
  - Board of directors, 1979 (Box 12)
  - Board of directors, 1980 (Box 12)
  - Board of directors, 1981 (Box 12)
  - Board of directors, 1982 (Box 12)
  - Board of directors, 1983 (Box 12)
  - Board of directors, 1984 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1985 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1986 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1987 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1988 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1990 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1991 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1992 (Box 13)
  - Board of directors, 1993 (Box 14)
  - Board of directors, 1994 (Box 14)
  - Board of directors, 1995 (Box 14)
  - Board of directors, 1996 (Box 14)
  - Board of directors, 1997 (Box 14)
  - Board of directors, 1998 (Box 14)
  - Board of directors, 1999 (Box 14)
  - Board of directors, 2000-2001 (3 folders) (Box 15)
  - Board of directors, 2002 (2 folders) (Box 15)
  - Board of directors’ book, 1982-1983 (Box 16)
  - Board of directors’ book, 1986-1987 (Box 16)
  - Board of directors’ book, 1996-1998 (Box 16)
  - Board of directors’ book, 1999-2000 (Box 16)
  - Business advisory committee (Box 16)
  - Merger proposal, UCSC Extension, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Merger proposal, Center for Training and Careers, 2001 (Box 17)
  - Organizational charts (Box 17)
  - Personnel (Box 17)
  - Statistics, 1980-1985 (Box 17)
  - Statistics, 1994-1998 (Box 17)
  - Statistics, 1999 (Box 17)
  - Statistics, 2000 (2 folders) (Box 17)
  - Statistics, 2001 (Box 18)
  - Statistics, volunteers (Box 18)
- Series III. FINANCIAL RECORDS
  Scope and Contents note
  This series includes financial records, such as budget reports, and materials related to fund development activities, such as the Pinnacle and Circle of Friends luncheons.
  - Financial records, 1973-1980 (Box 18)
  - Financial records, 1980-1988 (Box 18)
  - Financial records, 1990-1996 (Box 18)
  - Financial records, 1997-1999 (2 folders) (Box 18)
  - Financial records, 2000-2002 (Box 18)
  - Fund development, 1978-1979 (Box 19)
  - Fund development, 1980-1989 (Box 19)
  - Fund development, 1991-2001 (Box 19)
  - Fund development, affiliate luncheons, 1973-1989 (Box 19)
  - Fund development, fund raising institute (Box 19)
  - Fund development, fund raising school, 1980 (2 folders) (Box 19)
  - Fund development, Women of Vision, 1984-1994 (Box 20)
  - Fund development, Women of Vision, 1995-2000 (Box 20)
  - Fund development, Pinnacle, 1990-1999 (Box 20)
  - Fund development, circle of friends, 1995-2000 (Box 21)
  - Fund development, circle of friends, 1998 (2 folders) (Box 21)
  - Fund development, campaign for a new era, 1997 (Box 21)
  - Fund development, Morrell (Box 21)
  - Fund development, Lyman (Box 21)
  - Fund development, Wright (Box 21)
- Series IV. PROGRAMS AND PUBLICATIONS
  This series includes various newsletters, publications (such as the Resource Guide), clippings, and course offerings.
  - Publications by other organizations, 1964-1980 (3 folders) (Box 22)
  - Talent Source, 1973-1985 (3 folders) (Box 22)
  - Resource center publications, 1974-1977 (Box 23)
  - Affirmative Answers, 1974-1976 (5 folders) (Box 23)
  - Hewlett Packard equal opportunity workshop, 1974 (Box 23)
  - Seminars and workshops, 1974-1986 (Box 24)
  - Course offerings, 1975-1979 (Box 24)
  - As of Yesterday, 1975-1980 (Box 24)
  - Resource Center standards, 1976 (Box 24)
  - Training for Finding a Job, 1976 (Box 24)
  - Affirmative Action Update, 1976-1979 (Box 24)
  - Resume workshops and handbooks, 1977-1982 (Box 24)
  - Catalyst conference, 1978 (Box 24)
  - Resources, 1981-1983 (Box 24)
  - Resources, 1984-1988 (Box 24)
  - Career Connections, 1986-1988 (Box 24)
  - Connections, 1988-1995 (Box 25)
  - Catalog, 1991-1995 (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Annual report, 1993 (Box 25)
  - The Buzz, 1993-1995 (Box 25)
  - Corporate Connections, 1994-1998 (Box 25)
  - Volunteer Connections, 1994-1999 (Box 25)
  - Career Action Connections, 1995-1997 (Box 25)
  - Counseling Connections, 1995-1996 (Box 25)
  - Slightly Off Center, 1996-2000 (Box 25)
  - Member Connections, 1997-1999 (Box 25)
  - Resource Guide, 1998-1999 (Box 25)
  - Resource Guide, 2000-2002 (Box 25)
  - Speaker series, 1998 (2 folders) (Box 25)
  - Speaker series, 2000 (Box 26)
  - Book draft, 2000 (Box 26)
  - Clippings, 1973-1979 (Box 26)
  - Clippings, 1980-1989 (Box 26)
  - Clippings, 1990-1999 (Box 26)
  - Clippings, 2000-2002 (Box 26)
  - Press releases, 1975-1978 (Box 26)
  - Studies and articles (Box 27)
  - Miscellaneous programs and publications (4 folders) (Box 27)
- Series V. AUDIO/VISUAL MATERIALS
  This series includes VHS and audio tapes of Career Action Center events, news and publicity related to the Center, and interviews with founding members.
  - Lew Platt, Hewlett Packard, Career Self Reliance (2 VHS tapes) (Box 28)
  - Career Action Center, Access Los Altos (VHS) (Box 28)
  - Career Action Center P.R. (2 VHS tapes) (Box 28)
  - Community Network, 1998 (VHS) (Box 28)
  - Channel 7 News, 1988 (VHS) (Box 28)
  - Channel 7, Guilbault, 1989 (VHS) (Box 28)
  - Women of Vision, 1990 (VHS) (Box 28)
  - Women of Vision, 1992 (VHS) (Box 28)
  - Women of Vision, 1994 (2 VHS tapes) (Box 28)
  - Women of Vision, 1995 (2 VHS tapes) (Box 29)
  - Women of Vision, 1997 (VHS) (Box 29)
  - Women of Vision, 1998 (2 VHS tapes) (Box 29)
  - Women of Vision, Gardner/Bray, 1999 (2 VHS tapes) (Box 29)
  - Women of Vision, 1999 (VHS) (Box 29)
  - Women of Vision, 2000 (VHS) (Box 29)
  - Donor party, 1990 (VHS) (Box 29)
  - Pinnacle, 1992 (VHS) (Box 29)
  - Platinum Sponsor roundtable, 1993 (VHS) (Box 29)
  - Body Speed breakfast run, 1993 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - Orientation tape, 1993 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - Orientation tape (VHS) (Box 30)
  - Donor/Friend party, 1993 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - Twentieth year, 1993 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - PBS, The World of Work, 1996 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - SUN, 1996 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - Toward a Resilient Workforce, 1995 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - Hewlett Packard, 1997-1998 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - PBS, Digital Divide I, 2000 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - PBS, Digital Divide II, 2000 (VHS) (Box 30)
  - Vision to Success (video cassette for broadcasting) (Box 31)
  - Interviews with Marylyn Morrel and Jing Lyman (audio) (Box 31)
  - Interviews with Diane Saign, Ellie shelly, Peggy Larsen (audio) (Box 31)
  - Share the Vision, 1998 (2 audio tapes) (Box 31)
  - Career Action Center, 1997 (audio) (Box 31)
  - Women of Vision, 1997 (3 audio tapes) (Box 31)
  - Pinnacle (audio) (Box 31)
  - Pinnacle, 1997 (2 audio tapes) (Box 31)
  - Pinnacle, 1998 (2 audio tapes) (Box 31)
  - National Career Fitness (audio) (Box 31)